Guide to the Naomi Shihab Nye Papers
The Wittliff Collections
Naomi Shihab Nye Papers
1955 - 2010s
1970s - 2010s
The Wittliff Collections https://www.thewittliffcollections.txstate.edu
Nye, Naomi Shihab; Duncan, Virginia
SWWC.133
30 Linear Feet
55 boxes 48 document boxes and 7 oversized boxes
Naomi Shihab Nye, acclaimed poet who also writes essays, songs, novels, and children's books; edits poetry anthologies, and teaches poetry writing to youth and adults, was born in 1952 in St. Louis, Missouri to Aziz Shihab, a journalist and immigrant from Palestine, and Miriam Shihab, a Montessori teacher with a fine arts degree in painting. Forty-eight document boxes and seven oversized boxes containing drafts, diaries and notebooks, photographic material, correspondence, and published material document the working life of poet, writer, and educator Naomi Shihab Nye (1952- ).
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchase, 2017.
Biographical Note
Overview
Naomi Shihab Nye, acclaimed poet who also writes essays, songs, novels, and children's books; edits poetry anthologies, and teaches poetry writing to youth and adults, was born in 1952 in St. Louis, Missouri to Aziz Shihab, a journalist and immigrant from Palestine, and Miriam Shihab, a Montessori teacher with a fine arts degree in painting. Nye has won numerous awards, including her first major recognition for Hugging the Jukebox as a National Poetry Series selection in 1982, critical acclaim for her 2011 short story collection There Is No Long Distance Now: Very Short Stories, Best Books for Young Adults several times from the American Library Association, and the gratitude of San Antonio Independent School District teachers for her poetry teaching packets. Nye is a Lannan Fellow, a Guggenheim Fellow, and Poetry Foundation Young People's Poet Laureate for 2019-2021. Nye referred to herself as an "itinerant writer," referring to the twelve years from 1974-1986 she spent teaching poetry in schools around Texas, while also writing and publishing. Nye lists her early influences, starting at age five, as Carl Sandberg, Margaret Wise Brown, Emily Dickinson, William Blake, and Louisa May Alcott. High School and college influences include Henry David Thoreau, Jack Kerouac, Gregory Corso, Gary Snyder, Gertrude Stein, and William Stafford; the last of whom Nye was able to work with, and she became friends with Stafford and his family.
Nye began writing early in life, publishing poetry at age 7 and continuing throughout her childhood. She wrote a column for teens in high school, and while teaching across Texas and the country she continued to write and publish. While teaching children poetry during the Gulf War, which began in 1991, Nye read the students poetry written by Iraqi writers, and ultimately edited This Same Sky: A Collection of Poems from Around the World, which includes 129 poets from 68 countries. Her young adult novel Going Going, 2005, is an attempt to recognize and document her neighborhood in San Antonio, Texas as it changed due to gentrification. This attention to the connection of people across the world, and their local daily realities, imbues Nye's work. For Nye, the best audience is children, and she does not recognize a distinction between adult and children's writing. While writing poetry for adults in the 1970s and 1980s, Nye searched for cross-over texts to use with the young people she was teaching. In the 1990s her editor Virginia Duncan suggested she write for children, which she did with Sitti's Secrets, and continues today. To date, Nye has published audio recordings of songs she wrote and sang; children's books, including picture books, poetry, poetry anthologies, and young adult novels; written and edited poetry for adults; served as a columnist for Organica and poetry editor for The Texas Observer; and contributed to numerous poetry anthologies and periodicals.
Early Life and Family
Naomi Nye and her family moved to Jerusalem when she was in high school, around 1965, where she met her father's family for the first time. Nye attended a school that instructed in Arabic, Armenian, and English, though she only knew English. After the 6-Day War in 1967, she moved with her parents and brother to San Antonio, Texas, where she still resides. Nye graduated from high school in Texas without ever having attended a football game, and in honor of this accomplishment the football players bought her a mum. Nye attended Trinity University in San Antonio and lived with her parents. She graduated summa cum laude in 1974 with a degree in English and World Religions. In 1978, Nye married Michael Nye, a lawyer-turned-photographer, and in 1986 they had a son, Madison Cloudfeather. After college, Naomi and Michael traveled extensively in Mexico and Central America, which produced many unpublished poems from this time period, and in response to the Mexican American culture in San Antonio but lack of Mexican culture, the anthology The Tree Is Older than You Are: A Bilingual Gathering of Poems and Stories from Mexico with Paintings by Mexican Artists, decades later in 1995. Nye continued her high school work of essayist, writing numerous articles on topics from poetry to politics to housework for various newspapers, served as a columnist for Organica: A Magazine of Art and Activism.
Non-Writing Work
Nye was the most active employee at the Texas Commission on the Arts Writers in the Schools Project, working across Texas and publishing chapbook and poetry. She stopped this work in 1986 when her son was born. Nye also worked as a visiting instructor or writer in residence across US colleges and schools, as well as internationally, including at the University of California at Berkeley, the University of Hawai'i Manoa, the University of Texas at Austin and at San Antonio, and Texas State University in San Marcos. Nye also contributed to two PBS television series, the "Language of Life" with Bill in 1995, and "The United States of Poetry" in 1996. As a young woman in the late 1970s, Nye wrote songs and played guitar and sang in coffee shops and for schoolchildren. She recorded an album of children's songs, Rutabaga-Roo in 1979, and an album of folk songs, Lullaby Raft in 1981. Nye writes for adults and children, is adept in multiple genres, finds home in her backyard and wherever in the world she travels, and teaches and edits anthologies as well as writes poetry. Similarly, she is both loving and accepting of all people, and a fierce activist for peace and justice.
Sources
"Naomi Nye." Gale Literature: Contemporary Authors, Gale, 2020. Gale in Context: Biography, https://link-gale-com.libproxy.txstate.edu/apps/doc/H1000117919/BIC?u=txshracd2550&sid=BIC&xid=28da7104. Accessed 22 Apr. 2020. Naomi Nye Papers, The Wittliff Collections, Texas State University.
List of Works Works For Children Sitti's Secrets, illustrated by Nancy Carpenter, Four Winds Press (New York, NY), 1994 Benito's Dream Bottle, illustrated by Yu Cha Pak, Simon & Schuster (New York, NY), 1995 Lullaby Raft, illustrated by Vivienne Flesher, Simon & Schuster (New York, NY), 1997. Habibi (young-adult novel), Simon & Schuster (New York, NY), 1997. Come with Me: Poems for a Journey, illustrated by Dan Yaccarino, Greenwillow Books (New York, NY), 2000. Nineteen Varieties of Gazelle: Poems of the Middle East, HarperCollins (New York, NY), 2002. Baby Radar, illustrated by Nancy Carpenter, HarperCollins (New York, NY), 2003. A Maze Me: Poems for Girls, illustrated by Terre Maher, Greenwillow Books (New York, NY), 2005. Going Going (young-adult novel), Greenwillow Books (New York, NY), 2005. Honeybee: Poems and Short Prose, Greenwillow Books (New York, NY), 2008. The Turtle of Oman (novel), illustrated by Betsy Peterschmidt, Greenwillow Books, an imprint of Harper Collins Publishers (New York, NY), 2014. Works For Children; Editor This Same Sky: A Collection of Poems from Around the World, Four Winds Press (New York, NY), 1992. The Tree Is Older than You Are: A Bilingual Gathering of Poems and Stories from Mexico with Paintings by Mexican Artists, Simon & Schuster (New York, NY), 1995. (With Paul B. Janeczko) I Feel a Little Jumpy around You: A Book of Her Poems and His Poems Collected in Pairs, Simon & Schuster (New York, NY), 1996. The Space between Our Footsteps: Poems and Paintings from the Middle East, Simon & Schuster (New York, NY), 1998, published as The Flag of Childhood: Poems from the Middle East, Aladdin Paperbacks (New York, NY), 2002. What Have You Lost?, photographs by husband, Michael Nye, Greenwillow Books (New York, NY), 1999. Salting the Ocean: One Hundred Poems by Young Poets, illustrated by Ashley Bryan, Greenwillow Books (New York, NY), 2000. Is This Forever, or What? Poems and Paintings from Texas, Greenwillow Books (New York, NY), 2004. Works For Adults Tattooed Feet, Texas Portfolio (Texas City, TX), 1977. Eye-to-Eye, Texas Portfolio (Texas City, TX), 1978. Different Ways to Pray, Breitenbush Publications (Portland, OR), 1980. On the Edge of the Sky, Iguana (Madison, WI), 1981. Hugging the Jukebox, Dutton (New York, NY), 1982. Yellow Glove, Breitenbush Books (Portland, OR), 1986. Invisible, Trilobite Press (Denton, TX), 1987. (Translator of poetry, with Salma Khadra Jayyusi) Fadwa Tuqan, A Mountainous Journey: An Autobiography, translated by Olive Kenny, edited by Jayyusi, Graywolf Press (St. Paul, MN), 1990. (Translator, with May Jayyusi) Muhammad al-Maghut, The Fan of Swords: Poems, edited and introduced by Salma Khadra Jayyusi, Three Continents Press (Washington, DC), 1991. Mint, State Street Press (Brockport, NY), 1991. Travel Alarm, Wings Press (San Antonio, TX), 1992. Red Suitcase, BOA Editions (Brockport, NY), 199.. Words under the Words: Selected Poems, Far Corner Books/Eighth Mountain Press (Portland, OR), 1995. Fuel, BOA Editions (Rochester, NY), 1998. Mint Snowball, Anhinga Press (Tallahassee, FL), 2001. You and Yours, BOA Editions (Rochester, NY), 2005. (Editor) Between Heaven and Texas, University of Texas Press (Austin, TX), 2006. Tender Spot, Bloodaxe Books (Northumberland, England), 2008. (Selector) Time You Let Me In: 25 Poets under 25, Greenwillow Books (New York, NY), 2010. Transfer: Poems, BOA Editions (Rochester, NY), 2011. Famous: Poem, illustrated by Lisa Desimini, Wings Press (San Antonio, TX), 2015. Voices in the Air: Poems for Listeners, Greenwillow Books (New York, NY), 2018. Cast Away: Poems for Our Time, Greenwillow Books (New York, NY), 2019. The Tiny Journalist: Poems, BOA Editions (Rochester, NY), 2019. Everything Comes Next: Collected and New Poems, Greenwillow Books (New York, NY ), 2020. Recordings Rutabaga-Roo: I've Got a Song and It's for You (children's songs), Flying Cat (San Antonio, TX), 1979. Lullaby Raft(folk songs), Flying Cat (San Antonio, TX), 1981. The Spoken Page (poetry), International Poetry Forum, 1988. The Poet and the Poem, Library of Congress Archive of Recorded Poetry and Literature (Washington, DC), 2000. Other Never in a Hurry: Essays on People and Places, University of South Carolina Press (Columbia, SC), 1996. I'll Ask You Three Times, Are You OK? Tales of Driving and Being Driven, Greenwillow Books (New York, NY), 2007.(Author of foreword) Cary Clack, Clowns and Rats Scare Me: Columns, Trinity University Press (San Antonio, TX), 2009. There Is No Long Distance Now: Very Short Stories, Greenwillow Books (New York, NY), 2011. With Christopher Omelas), Name Them--They Fly Better: Pat Hammond's Theory of Aerodynamics, Maverick Books, an imprint of Trinity University Press (San Antonio, Texas), 2017.
Contributor, including What You Wish for: Stories and Poems for Darfur, edited by Alexander McCall Smith, G.P. Putnam's Sons (New York, NY), 2011. Columnist for Organica Columnist for Texas Observer Poetry in America: Favorite Poems, Library of Congress Archive of Recorded Poetry and Literature (Washington, DC), 2000.
Scope and Contents
Forty-eight document boxes and seven oversized boxes containing drafts, diaries and notebooks, photographic material, correspondence, and published material document the working life of poet, writer, and educator Naomi Shihab Nye (1952-). The collection has been arranged into seven series: Series I: Personal and Biographical; Series II: Works; Series III: Correspondence; Series IV: Instruction; Series V: Appearances and Awards; Series VI: Writings on Nye; and Series VII: Works by Others. Multiple drafts of published and unpublished songs, poems, short stories, and essays document Nye's creative work from an early age through high school, college, and adulthood. While her own books are not as well documented, Nye's work as editor of several poetry collections is well-documented. Of note is correspondence with long-time editor Virginia Duncan, which documents their working relationship as well as several projects. Also of note is Shihab Nye's teaching work, documented via poems written by children, clippings, and reports.
Related Materials
A collection of 53.6 linear feet (115 boxes and 1 drawer of oversize material) of additional Naomi Shihab Nye Papers are held at the University of Texas at San Antonio Special Collections, described here: https://txarchives.org/utsa/finding_aids/00125.xml.
Index Terms
Subjects
American poetry -- Texas
Document Types
Juvenile poetry
Places
Arab American poetry; Poetry-in-the-Schools Program; Women poets
Subjects (Persons)
Nye, Naomi Shihab
- Personal and Biographical, 1958-2010s; 1.5 boxes
  Scope and Contents
  Personal and Biographical materials contain legal, family, and biographical materials, and photographic materials. Legal documents include contracts and copyright papers for very early works and songs, library card, vaccinations and passport. Biographical material includes multiple vitas, online biographies and publication lists, and school and family documents. Of note is a college reunion questionnaire and a Guggenheim application with reference letter from Charles Busch. Photographs many headshots and portraits, including some by photographer and husband Michael Nye. Certain events are well documented in photographs, including gatherings of family and friends, and work-related events.
  - Legal documents, 1970-1982 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical documents, 1972-1974, 1996-2003 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Guggenheim 84/85", 1984-1990 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Multiple vitas, correspondence from The Academy of American Poets and Guggenheim, published reviews, "Charles Busch's legendary wild Guggenheim reference."
  - School documents, 1958-1974 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Family documents, 1964, 1966, 1982-1994 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Photographs, 1955 - circa 2010s
    - Headshots and Portraits, circa 1970s - circa 2010s
      - By Michael Nye, circa 1970s; 3 5x7 b&w photographs (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Various, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
        33 color and b&w photographs of various sizes, including 8x10, contact sheet with son as a toddler, driver's license, and university ID
    - Family and Friends, 1955-2009
      - Family and Childhood (Box 1, Folder 8)
        Includes photos of Aziz Nye, older photographs of ancestors, "Sitti Khadra, my Palestinian grandma about 96 years old-photo by Michael Nye," and "Park Slope, Brooklyn, NY 1970, Rochelle Cohen, Béla the Cat, Baba Nazz."
      - Boot Springs pagan celebration, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 9)
        Related Materials
        Also see Diary, "Big Bend, Thanksgiving 1973," in Box 2, folder 11.
      - Nye with others, circa 1970s – circa 1990s (Box 1, Folder 10)
        (21) color and b&w photographs of various sizes.
      - W. S. Merwin, 1968, Jan. 1990-July 7, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - "Jerusalem", 1993 (Box 1, Folder 12)
        Includes prose poem by Nye.
      - Robert Bonazzi, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
        (2) 4x6 color photographs, one with Nye.
      - Dorothy Stafford videos, 2005, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 14)
        Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
        (2) optical discs containing moving images.
      - "Aziz & Naomi, Rough Cut", 2007 (Box 1, Folder 15)
        (1) optical disc containing moving images
    - Events, 1976-2014
      - Notre Dame Literary Festival, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 16)
        By William Stafford, include Ken Kesey, William Goyen, John Phillip Santos, Naomi Shihab Nye, and others.
      - Reading event and photography exhibit, March, 1985, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - International Poetry Forum, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 18)
        Dinner, introduction by Sam Hazo, reading and signing.
      - "Falls Church, VA", circa 1995 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - "Naomi Shihab Tree Dedication", circa 2006 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - Dodge Poetry Festival, Sept. 26, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - "Our Storm King Art Center Weekend", October 24-25, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - "ATFP Gala: Selected gala pictures", 2010; (1) optical disc (Box 2, Folder 2)
        Still images of the American Task Force on Palestine Gala, 2010. ATFP Award for Excellence in the Arts.
      - Golden Rose Award, June 26, 2011 (Box 49, Folder 1)
        Series of (5) 8 x 10 color photographs by Malcolm Greenway.
      - "Haystack Book of Words", Oct. 11, 2011 (Box 2, Folder 3)
        (1) optical disk
      - "PoetryLife", 2013 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - "Naomi Shihab Nye, ASD", 2014 (Box 2, Folder 5)
        Photos from American School of Doha in Doha, Qatar.
      - Other events, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
        Includes instruction, singing with guitar, and readings.
    - Unidentified, undated
      - Photographs of others (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - Unidentified negatives and slides, Includes slides (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Works, 1963-2017; 30 boxes
  The largest series by far is Works. Subseries include Diaries, Notebooks, Appointment Books, Artwork, Early Work, Music, Poems, Monographs-Poetry, Monographs-Edited Poetry, Monographs-Prose, Editor Correspondence, Short Stories, Essays, Publications, Artbooks, Broadsides, and Talks.
  Diaries and Notebooks are arranged chronologically and include diary entries starting at age eight, and ideas and drafts for poems and longer writings. Individual works are noted where possible. Artwork and Early Work document a small amount of grade school, high school, and college creative work. Music contains many songs arranged alphabetically by title; some songs include chords, notes, and corrections, and there is some overlap in titles with Poems.
  Poems make up the bulk of this series, with 7 ½ boxes of poems, including unpublished works and early writings from Nye's travels in Central and South America in the 1970s. Poems are arranged alphabetically by title, and vary from single drafts of unmarked poems, to multiple drafts with annotations and corrections. There is overlap in titles with Music, Monographs, and Publications.
  Monographs-Poetry, Monographs-Edited Poetry, and Monographs-Prose contain materials related to published books for children and adults, arranged by publication date. Contents vary widely by title from one letter or review, to multiple drafts and correspondence.
  Editor Correspondence contains letters and faxes between Nye and longtime editor Virginia Duncan and documents their relationship as well as the creation and production of various monographs. This correspondence is placed within the Works series because it often contains full drafts or items that relate to more than one work. As there is overlap with Monographs, researchers are encouraged to review both subseries when investigating a particular work. Some correspondence between Duncan and others, in reference to Nye's works, is also included.
  Stories, Essays, Publications, Art Books, Broadsides, and Talks complete the Works Series. Short Stories and Essays are arranged alphabetically by title. Materials vary from single draft to multiple drafts with annotations and comments. Publications, Art Books, and Broadsides are arranged chronologically and include poems published in journals, and special/limited run publications. Talks are often are not labeled or dated, and they are generally notes for speeches.
  - Diaries, 1963-1973
    - 1963 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      Daily diary, ages 10 and 11. Small white plastic child's diary.
    - 1968 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      Daily diary, ages 15 and 16. Includes 6 small black and white snapshots of Nye and friends. Small green "One year diary."
    - "Big Bend Thanksgiving", 1973 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      Near-daily writings on camping trip with friends. Includes sketch of camp and a self-portrait in ballpoint pen. 17 pages. Brown cover.
      See also Photographs, Boot Springs pagan celebration, 1973. Box 1, folder 9.
  - Notebooks, 1972-circa 2010
    - September 3, 1972 - circa May 1973 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Early poems, ideas, and notes for poems, quotes and transcribed poems of others, notes for college schoolwork. 93 pages.
    - Circa 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Many transcribed poems of others. Includes poems by Nye "For Adlai," and "For my Overalls." 67 pages.
    - Circa August 7, 1974 - circa September 18, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Poems and prose writings. About 100 pages. "Son of Big Chief" writing tablet.
    - Circa January 15, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Drafts and annotated poems. Includes "Texas series," and prose poem. 19 pages.
    - May 22, 1975 - circa June 1975 (Box 49, Folder 2)
      Oversized journal from trip to Canada. Includes laid in watercolor, various sketches, diary entries and notes, and laid- in correspondence to family. Two color snapshots of Nye and others.
    - "Poetry workbook", circa 1976 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      Annotated poems, "The Little Things Which Keep us Alive," "The Violin Teacher," "Lunch With the Cousins," "The Surgeon," "Bad Days," "She Sits in the Living Room," "Four Late Songs," "The World's Largest Pecan," "Kansas," "What the Indian is Looking At," "Man with a Clarinet," "Girl on the Rock, Galveston, Texas," "Roller-skating in 1976," "For Thomas Wolfe, If He'll Take It," "My Father and the Fig Tree," "Days Like This," "How Arabs Have Babies," "The Worst Agony is You Driving Away," notes for songs and chords, and a hand-written resume. 67 pages.
    - June 6, 1976 - circa February 1982 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      Several diary entries, notes, and poems. 71 pages.
    - October 6, 1976 - undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - "Guatemala", July 22, 1977 - circa July 29, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 8)
      Diary entries, "poem notes," and draft of poem "At the Jungle." Laid in travel itinerary, and research. 53 pages.
    - "Plans of Action, SAISD, 1977-78 (Exercise ideas)", 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 9)
      Writing prompts and descriptions, poem draft "My Body is a Mystery." 42 pages.
    - "Songs", Before 1978 (Box 3, Folder 10)
      Includes "Hurricane," "San Antonio," "The Roof Song," "Falcons," "Old Songs," "Blues," "Song for Dick Poteet," "Stetson Song," "Wandering," "Uncle Frank Song," "The Kingsville Auction," "The New Song," "One Dime," and many other drafts, notes, and chords. About 44 pages.
    - January 21, 1978 - May 31, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 11)
      Poetry drafts, sketches, "Sweet Home Saga," stories about driving across Texas, poem "Afternoon in Kerrville, Texas." 30 pages.
    - September 1978 (Box 3, Folder 12)
      Poems, notes to self. Includes original annotated draft of poem "Kindness," also "A Survey of Bread in Popayan Colombia," "One Thing Beside Another Does Not Shine," "The Stolen Camera," "A Letter Home," "Neruda," notes for poems, "It Is What It Is." 31 pages.
    - September 4, 1978 - circa October 11, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      Journal kept during Nye's honeymoon in South America. Mostly diary entries, some poem ideas and drafts. Includes laid-in correspondence from Aziz Shihab. 106 pages.
    - Before 1980 (Box 4, Folder 2)